That's right.
هذا صحيح.
(Laughter)
(تصفيق)
and relate to the feelings of brown people,
والتواصل مع مشاعر الأشخاص ذوي البشرة البنية،
like my grandfather, a conservative Muslim guy.
مثل جدي، رجل مسلم محافظ.
And also, I could understand my Afghan mother, my Pakistani father,
ويمكنني فهم أمي الأفغانية، وأبي الباكستاني،
not so religious but laid-back, fairly liberal.
ليسا متدينان ولكن هادئان ومتحرران تمامًا.
And of course, I could understand
وبطبيعة الحال، يمكنني أن أفهم
and relate to the feelings of white people.
مشاعر ذوي البشرة البيضاء وأتواصل معها.
The white Norwegians of my country.
النرويجيون ذوي البشرة البيضاء من بلدي.
You know, white, brown, whatever --
كما تعلمون، ذوي البشرة البيضاء والبنية، أيًا كان -
I loved them all.
أحببتهم جميعًا.
I understood them all,
أتفهمهم جميعًا،
even if they didn't always understand each other;
حتى لو لم يكونوا دائماً متفاهمين مع بعضهم البعض؛
they were all my people.
كانوا جميعًا أفراد مجتمعي.
My father, though, was always really worried.
كان والدي، رغم ذلك، قلقًا دائمًا.
He kept saying that even with the best education,
وظل يردد أنه حتى بالحصول على تعليم جيد،
I was not going to get a fair shake.
لن أحصل على فرصة عادلة.
I would still face discrimination, according to him.
وسأواجه ذلك التمييز، وفقًا لحديثه.
And that the only way to be accepted by white people
والطريقة الوحيدة ليتقبلك الأشخاص البيض
would be to become famous.
هي أن أصبح مشهورة.
Now, mind you, he had this conversation with me when I was seven years old.
الآن، أذكركم، أجرى هذه المحادثة معي عندما كنت في السابعة من العمر.
So while I'm seven years old, he said,
عندما كنت في السابعة من العمر، قال لي:
"Look, so it's either got to be sports, or it's got to be music."
"اسمعي، إما أن تكون الرياضة، أو أن تكون الموسيقى."
He didn't know anything about sports -- bless him -- so it was music.
لا يملك أدنى فكرة عن الرياضة - ليباركه الله - لذلك كان الحل الموسيقى.
So when I was seven years old, he gathered all my toys, all my dolls,
لذلك عندما كنت في السابعة من العمر، جمع كل ألعابي، كل الدمى،
and he threw them all away.
وألقى بها في القمامة.
In exchange he gave me a crappy little Casio keyboard and --
في المقابل أعطاني لوحة مفاتيح تافهة من نوع كازيو --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah. And singing lessons.
نعم، ودروس في الغناء.
And he forced me, basically, to practice for hours and hours every single day.
وأجبرني، في الأساس، على التدرب لساعات وساعات كل يوم.
Very quickly, he also had me performing for larger and larger audiences,
بسرعة جدًا، جعلني أيضا أقدّم أداءً لجمهور أكبر وأكبر،
and bizarrely, I became almost a kind of poster child
وبشكل غريب، أصبحت تقريباً من الأطفال الذين يظهرون على الملصقات
for Norwegian multiculturalism.
التابعة للتعددية الثقافية النرويجية.
I felt very proud, of course.
شعرت بالفخر، بالطبع.
Because even the newspapers at this point
لأنه حتى الصحف بدأت في هذه المرحلة
were starting to write nice things about brown people,
تكتب أشياء جميلة عن ذوي البشرة السمراء،
so I could feel that my superpower was growing.
لذلك يمكنني أن أشعر أن قوتي الخارقة تنمو.
So when I was 12 years old, walking home from school,
عندما كنت في 12 من العمر، خلال عودتي إلى المنزل من المدرسة،
I took a little detour
عدت أدراجي
because I wanted to buy my favorite sweets called "salty feet."
لأنني أردت شراء حلوياتي المفضلة تسمى "القدم المالحة".
I know they sound kind of awful,
أعلم أنها تبدو فظيعة نوعًا ما،
but I absolutely love them.
ولكن أحبها حقًا.
They're basically these little salty licorice bits in the shape of feet.
أساسًا هي عبارة عن قطع صغيرة من عرق السوس المالحة في شكل قدم.
And now that I say it out loud, I realize how terrible that sounds,
والآن بعد قول ذلك بصوت عال، أدرك مدى الفظاعة التي يبدو عليها الأمر،
but be that as it may, I absolutely love them.
ولكن رغم ذلك، أنا أحبها تمامًا.
So on my way into the store,
في طريقي إلى المتجر،
there was this grown white guy in the doorway blocking my way.
كان هناك رجل أبيض بالغ في المدخل يسد الطريق أمامي.
So I tried to walk around him, and as I did that, he stopped me
لذلك حاولت أن أتفاداه، وقمت بذلك، أوقفني
and he was staring at me,
وحدّق فيَ،
and he spit in my face, and he said,
وبصق في وجهي، وقال:
"Get out of my way
ّابتعدي عن طريقي
you little black bitch, you little Paki bitch,
أيتها العاهرة السوداء، أيتها العاهرة الباكستانية،
go back home where you came from."
عودي من حيث أتيت."
I was absolutely horrified.
كنت خائفةً حقًا.
I was staring at him.
كنت أحدق فيه.
I was too afraid to wipe the spit off my face,
كنت خائفةً جدًا من مسح البصاق من وجهي،
even as it was mixing with my tears.
بالرغم من أنه امتزج مع دموعي.
I remember looking around, hoping that any minute now,
أذكر أنني كنت أنظر حولي، على أمل أنه في أي لحظة،
a grown-up is going to come and make this guy stop.
سيأتي شخص بالغ ويوقف هذا الصبي عن حدّه.
But instead, people kept hurrying past me and pretended not to see me.
ولكن بدلاً من ذلك، واصل الناس طريقهم على عجل وتظاهروا بعدم رؤيتي.
I was very confused because I was thinking, well,
كنت مشوشة جدًا لأنني كنت أفكر، حسنًا،
"My white people, come on! Where are they? What's going on?
"أيها البيض، هيا! أين هم؟ ماذا يحدث هنا؟
How come they're not coming and rescuing me?"
كيف يعقل أنهم لم يأتوا لإنقاذي؟ "
So, needless to say, I didn't buy the sweets.
لا داعي أن أخبركم، لم اشتري الحلوى.
I just ran home as fast as I could.
ركضت نحو المنزل بأقصى سرعة فحسب.
Things were still OK, though, I thought.
كانت الأمور مع ذلك لا تزال على ما يرام، أظن.
As time went on, the more successful I became,
وبمضي الوقت، أصبحت أكثر نجاحًا،
I eventually started also attracting harassment from brown people.
بدأت أيضًا في نهاية المطاف أواجه التحرش من ذوي البشرة السمراء.
Some men in my parent's community felt that it was unacceptable
شعر بعض الرجال في مجتمع والدي أن ذلك أمر غير مقبول
and dishonorable for a woman to be involved in music
ومخز بالنسبة لامرأة أن تشارك في الموسيقى
and to be so present in the media.
وتتواجد في وسائل الإعلام.
So very quickly, I was starting to become attacked at my own concerts.
على نحو سريع جدًا، بدأت أتعرض للهجوم في حفلاتي الخاصة.
I remember one of the concerts, I was onstage, I lean into the audience
أتذكر في واحدة من الحفلات الموسيقية، كنت على خشبة المسرح، وملت ناحية من الجمهور
and the last thing I see is a young brown face,
وآخر شيء رأيته هو وجه شاب بني اللون،
and the next thing I know is some sort of chemical is thrown in my eyes
والشيء التالي الذي أعرفه نوعًا ما أنه تم إلقاء مواد كيميائية على عيني
and I remember I couldn't really see and my eyes were watering
وأتذكر أنني لم أستطيع رؤية أي شيء فعلاً وكانت عيناي تدمعان
but I kept singing anyway.
ولكنني واصلت الغناء على أي حال.
I was spit in the face in the streets of Oslo, this time by brown men.
تعرضت للبصق على وجهي في شوارع أوسلو، وهذه المرة من قبل ذوي البشرة السمراء.
They even tried to kidnap me at one point.
حتى أنهم حاولوا خطفي ذات مرة.
The death threats were endless.
وكانت التهديدات بالقتل لا تنتهي.
I remember one older bearded guy stopped me in the street one time,
أتذكر ايقافي في الشارع ذات مرة من قبل رجل مسن ملتحي،
and he said, "The reason I hate you so much
قال: "يعود سبب كرهي الشديد لك
is because you make our daughters think
لأنك تجعلين بناتنا يعتقدن
they can do whatever they want."
أن بإمكانهن القيام بأي شيء يردنه."
A younger guy warned me to watch my back.
حذرني شاب أن أكون متيقظة.
He said music is un-Islamic and the job of whores,
أخبرني أن الموسيقى غير إسلامية ووظيفة العاهرات،
and if you keep this up, you are going to be raped
وإذا واصلت هذا الأمر، سأتعرض للاغتصاب
and your stomach will be cut out so that another whore like you will not be born.
وسيتم قطع معدتك كي لا تنجبي عاهرة أخرى مثلك.
Again, I was so confused.
كنت مرتبكة جدًا مجددًا.
I couldn't understand what was going on.
لم أستطع فهم ما يحدث.
My brown people now starting to treat me like this -- how come?
أصبح المحيطون بي الآن يعاملونني بنفس الطريقة -- كيف يعقل ذلك؟
Instead of bridging the worlds, the two worlds,
بدلاً من إقامة رابط بين العوالم، العالمين،
I felt like I was falling between my two worlds.
شعرت أنني كنت أسقط بين عالمي.
I suppose, for me, spit was kryptonite.
أفترض، حسب اعتقادي، أن البصاق كان من الكريبتونيت.
So by the time I was 17 years old,
ببلوغي ال 17 من عمري،
the death threats were endless, and the harassment was constant.
كانت التهديدات بالقتل لا نهاية لها، وكان التحرش ثابتاً.
It got so bad, at one point my mother sat me down and said,
شعرت بالاستياء، ذات مرة جلست معي أمي وقالت لي:
"Look, we can no longer protect you, we can no longer keep you safe,
"اسمعي، لم يعد بإمكاننا حمايتك، ولم يعد بإمكاننا أن نبقيك آمنة،
so you're going to have to go."
لذا يجب عليك الرحيل."
So I bought a one-way ticket to London, I packed my suitcase and I left.
لذلك اشتريت تذكرة ذهاب في اتجاه واحد إلى لندن، جهزت حقيبتي وغادرت.
My biggest heartbreak at that point was that nobody said anything.
ما جعلني أشعر بحسرة كبيرة في تلك النقطة هو أنه لم يتجرأ أحد على قول شيء.
I had a very public exit from Norway.
كان خروجي من النرويج عاديًا جدًا .
My brown people, my white people -- nobody said anything.
لم يتفوه أحد بكلمة -- من أهلي ذوي البشرة السمراء والبيضاء.
Nobody said, "Hold on, this is wrong.
لم يقل أي شخص: "انتظري، هذا أمر خاطيء.
Support this girl, protect this girl, because she is one of us."
ادعموا هذه الفتاة، واحموا هذه الفتاة، لأنها واحدة منا."
Nobody said that.
لم يقل أحد ذلك.
Instead, I felt like -- you know at the airport,
بدلا من ذلك، شعرت مثل -- تعلمون في المطار،
on the baggage carousel you have these different suitcases
على حامل الأمتعة، يوجد حقائب مختلفة
going around and around,
تدور وتدور،
and there's always that one suitcase left at the end,
وهناك دائمًا حقيبة متروكة في الآخر،
the one that nobody wants, the one that nobody comes to claim.
تلك التي لا يريدها أحد، تلك التي لا يأتي أحد للمطالبة بها.
I felt like that.
انتابني ذلك الشعور.
I'd never felt so alone. I'd never felt so lost.
لم أشعر أنني وحيدة من قبل. لم أشعر أبدًا أنني ضائعة.
So, after coming to London, I did eventually resume my music career.
لذلك، بعد قدومي إلى لندن، استأنفت أخيرًا مسيرتي الموسيقية.
Different place, but unfortunately the same old story.
مكان مختلف، ولكن للأسف نفس القصة القديمة.
I remember a message sent to me saying that I was going to be killed
أتذكر رسالة وصلتني كان نصها أنني سأتعرض للقتل
and that rivers of blood were going to flow
وأن أنهراً من الدماء ستتدفق
and that I was going to be raped many times before I died.
وأنه سيتم أغتصابي عدة مرات قبل أن أموت.
By this point, I have to say,
عند هذه المرحلة، يجب أن أقول،
I was actually getting used to messages like this,
اعتدت في الواقع على وصول مثل هذه الرسائل،
but what became different was that now they started threatening my family.
ولكن ما اختلف هو أنهم بدأوا الآن يهددون عائلتي.
So once again, I packed my suitcase, I left music and I moved to the US.
لذلك مرة أخرى، حزمت حقيبتي، تركت الموسيقى وانتقلت إلى الولايات المتحدة.
I'd had enough.
لقد اكتفيت.
I didn't want to have anything to do with this anymore.
لم أعد أريد شيئاً يربطني بذلك بعد الآن.
And I was certainly not going to be killed for something
بالتأكيد لن أتعرض للقتل لشيء
that wasn't even my dream -- it was my father's choice.
لم يكن حتى حلمي -- كان اختيار والدي.
So I kind of got lost.
لذلك شعرت أنني تائهة.
I kind of fell apart.
شعرت نوعًا ما أنني انهار.
But I decided that what I wanted to do
ولكن قررت أن ما أردت فعله
is spend the next however many years of my life
هو قضاء السنوات القادمة من حياتي
supporting young people
في دعم الشباب
and to try to be there in some small way,
ومحاولة أن أكون موجودة بطرق بسيطة،
whatever way that I could.
مهما كانت الطريقة.
I started volunteering for various organizations
بدأت العمل التطوعي لصالح منظمات مختلفة
that were working with young Muslims inside of Europe.
تعمل مع الشباب المسلمين داخل أوروبا.
And, to my surprise, what I found was
وكانت دهشتي كبيرة، بسبب ما وجدت
so many of these young people were suffering and struggling.
كان الكثير من هؤلاء الشباب يعاني ويكافح.
They were facing so many problems with their families and their communities
كانوا يواجهون الكثير من المشاكل مع أسرهم ومجتمعاتهم المحلية
who seemed to care more about their honor and their reputation
الذي بدا أنهم يهتمون أكثر بشرفهم وسمعتهم
than the happiness and the lives of their own kids.
عوضًا عن السعادة وحياة أطفالهم.
I started feeling like maybe I wasn't so alone, maybe I wasn't so weird.
بدأت أشعر أنني لم أكن لوحدي، ربما لم أكن غريبة الأطوار.
Maybe there are more of my people out there.
ربما هناك المزيد من الأشخاص هناك.
The thing is, what most people don't understand
الشيء الذي لا يفهمه معظم الأشخاص
is that there are so many of us growing up in Europe
هو أنه يوجد الكثير منا ممن يترعرع في أوروبا
who are not free to be ourselves.
لا يتمتع بالحرية ليكون على طبيعته.
We're not allowed to be who we are.
لا يسمح لنا أن نكون على طبيعتنا.
We are not free to marry
لا نتمتع بالحرية لنتزوج
or to be in relationships with people that we choose.
أو نكون في علاقة مع أشخاص نختارهم.
We can't even pick our own career.
لا يمكننا حتى اختيار مهنتنا.
This is the norm in the Muslim heartlands of Europe.
هذا هو العرف في داخل المجتمع المسلم الموجود في أوروبا.
Even in the freest societies in the world, we're not free.
حتى في المجتمعات الأكثر حرية في العالم، لسنا أحرارً.
Our lives, our dreams, our future does not belong to us,
لا نملك حياتنا، وأحلامنا، ومستقبلنا
it belongs to our parents and their community.
إنما لوالدينا ومجتمعهم.
I found endless stories of young people
وجدت قصصًا لا تحصى عن شباب
who are lost to all of us,
تائهين عنا،
who are invisible to all of us
غير مرئيين لنا،
but who are suffering, and they are suffering alone.
ولكن يعانون، يعانون لوحدهم.
Kids we are losing to forced marriages, to honor-based violence and abuse.
نحن نخضع للزواج القسري، والعنف القائم على الشرف وسوء المعاملة.
Eventually, I realized after several years of working with these young people,
في نهاية المطاف، أدركت بعد عدة سنوات من العمل مع هؤلاء الشباب،
that I will not be able to keep running.
أنني لن أكون قادرة على الهروب.
I can't spend the rest of my life being scared and hiding
لا أستطيع قضاء بقية حياتي خائفة ومختبئة
and that I'm actually going to have to do something.
وأنه ينبغي عليّ فعلا القيام بشيء .
And I also realized that my silence, our silence,
وأدركت أيضًا أن صمتي، صمتنا،
allows abuse like this to continue.
يسمح بمواصلة إساءة معاملتنا.
So I decided that I wanted to put my childhood superpower to some use
لذا قررت استغلال قوة طفولتي العظمى
by trying to make people on the different sides of these issues understand
من خلال محاولة حث الناس على فهم الجوانب المختلفة للقضايا
what it's like to be a young person stuck between your family and your country.
فهم ما معنى أن تكون شابا عالقًا بين أسرتك وبلدك.
So I started making films, and I started telling these stories.
لذلك بدأت في صنع الأفلام، وبدأت برواية هذه القصص.
And I also wanted people to understand the deadly consequences of us
وأردت أيضاً أن يفهم الناس العواقب المميتة بالنسبة لنا
not taking these problems seriously.
لعدم أخذ هذه المشاكل على محمل الجد.
So the first film I made was about Banaz.
لذا كان أول فيلم قمت بإنتاجه عن "باناز".
She was a 17-year-old Kurdish girl in London.
كانت فتاة كردية في 17 من عمرها تعيش في لندن.
She was obedient, she did whatever her parents wanted.
كانت مطيعة، فعلت كل ما أراده منها والداها.
She tried to do everything right.
حاولت أن تفعل كل شيء بشكل صحيح.
She married some guy that her parents chose for her,
تزوجت رجلًا اختاره لها والداها،
even though he beat and raped her constantly.
على الرغم من أنه كان يضربها ويغتصبها باستمرار.
And when she tried to go to her family for help, they said,
وعندما حاولت طلب المساعدة من أسرتها، قالوا لها:
"Well, you got to go back and be a better wife."
"حسنا، عليك العودة وأن تكوني زوجة أفضل."
Because they didn't want a divorced daughter on their hands
لأنهم لا يريدون ابنة مطلقة بينهم
because, of course, that would bring dishonor on the family.
لأن ذلك، بالطبع، من شأنه أن يجلب العار للأسرة.
She was beaten so badly her ears would bleed,
تعرضت لضرب شديد ما جعل أذنيها تنزفان،
and when she finally left and she found a young man that she chose
وعندما غادرت أخيرًا، وجدت شابًا اختارته
and she fell in love with,
ووقعت في حبّه،
the community and the family found out
اكتشف المجتمع والأسرة الأمر
and she disappeared.
واختفت عن الأنظار.
She was found three months later.
عثر عليها بعد ثلاثة أشهر.
She'd been stuffed into a suitcase and buried underneath the house.
وضعت في حقيبة ودفنت تحت المنزل.
She had been strangled, she had been beaten to death
تعرضت للخنق، وللضرب حتى الموت
by three men, three cousins, on the orders of her father and uncle.
من قبل ثلاثة رجال، ثلاثة من أقاربها، بناءً على أوامر من والدها وعمها.
The added tragedy of Banaz's story
ما زاد في مأساة قصة بناز
is that she had gone to the police in England five times asking for help,
هو أن قامت بطلب المساعدة من الشرطة في إنجلترا خمس مرات،
telling them that she was going to be killed by her family.
مخبرة إياهم أن عائلتها ستقتلها.
The police didn't believe her so they didn't do anything.
لم تصدقها الشرطة لذلك لم يفعلوا أي شيء.
And the problem with this
وتتمحور المشكلة مع هذا
is that not only are so many of our kids facing these problems
في أنه ليس فقط الكثير من أطفالنا يواجهون هذه المشاكل
within their families and within their families' communities,
داخل أسرهم وداخل مجتمعات أسرهم،
but they're also meeting misunderstandings
ولكنهم أيضاً عرضة لسوء الفهم
and apathy in the countries that they grow up in.
واللامبالاة في البلدان التي يترعرعون فيها.
When their own families betray them, they look to the rest of us,
فعندما تخونهم أسرهم، فإنهن ينظرن إلينا،
and when we don't understand,
وعندما لا نفهمهن،
we lose them.
فإننا نخسرهن.
So while I was making this film, several people said to me,
لذلك خلال إعدادي لهذا الفيلم، قال لي العديد من الأشخاص،
"Well, Deeyah, you know, this is just their culture,
"حسنا، دياه، كما تعلمين، هذه ثقافتهم،
this is just what those people do to their kids
هذا ما يفعله هؤلاء الناس لأطفالهم
and we can't really interfere."
ولا يمكننا التدخل حقاً."
I can assure you being murdered is not my culture.
يمكنني أن أؤكد لكم أن القتل ليس موجوداً في ثقافتي.
You know?
هل تعلمون؟
And surely people who look like me,
وبالتأكيد الأشخاص الذين يشبهونني،
young women who come from backgrounds like me,
الشابات اللواتي ينحدرن من عائلات مثلي،
should be subject to the same rights, the same protections
ينبغي أن يخضعن لنفس الحقوق، لنفس الحماية
as anybody else in our country, why not?
مثل أي شخص آخر في بلدنا، لماذا لا؟
So, for my next film, I wanted to try and understand
لذلك، للفيلم المقبل، أردت أن أحاول وأفهم
why some of our young Muslim kids in Europe
لماذا يتجه بعض الأطفال المسلمون في أوروبا
are drawn to extremism and violence.
إلى التطرف والعنف.
But with that topic,
ولكن مع هذا الموضوع،
I also recognized that I was going to have to face my worst fear:
أدركت أيضاً أنني سأواجه أسوأ مخاوفي:
the brown men with beards.
الملتحين ذو البشرة السمراء.
The same men, or similar men,
نفس الرجال، أو رجال مماثلين،
to the ones that have hounded me for most of my life.
إلى أولئك الذين تعقبوني معظم حياتي.
Men that I've been afraid of most of my life.
الرجال الذين كنت خائفة منهم معظم حياتي.
Men that I've also deeply disliked,
الرجال الذين كنت أيضاً أكرهم بشدة،
for many, many years.
لسنوات عديدة.
So I spent the next two years interviewing convicted terrorists,
لذلك قضيت السنتين التاليتين في إجراء مقابلات مع إرهابيين مدانين،
jihadis and former extremists.
المجاهدين والمتطرفين السابقين.
What I already knew, what was very obvious already,
ما كنت أعرفه بالفعل، ما كان واضحاً جداً بالفعل،
was that religion, politics, Europe's colonial baggage,
أن الدين، والسياسة، الأمتعة الاستعمارية في أوروبا،
also Western foreign policy failures of recent years,
وأيضاً فشل السياسة الخارجية الغربية في السنوات الأخيرة،
were all a part of the picture.
كلها جزء من الأمر.
But what I was more interested in finding out was what are the human,
ولكن ما كنت مهتمة أكثر بمعرفته هو ماهية الإنسان،
what are the personal reasons
ما هي الأسباب الشخصية
why some of our young people are susceptible to groups like this.
لماذا بعض شبابنا يتأثرون بسرعة بمثل هذه المجموعات.
And what really surprised me was that I found wounded human beings.
وما فاجأني حقًا هو أنني وجدت أشخاصً مصابين.
Instead of the monsters that I was looking for,
بدلاً من الوحوش التي كنت أبحث عنها،
that I was hoping to find --
التي كنت آمل إيجادها --
quite frankly because it would have been very satisfying --
بشكل صريح لأنه كان يمكن أن يكون مقبولًا جدًا --
I found broken people.
وجدت أشخاصًا محطمين.
Just like Banaz,
أشخاصًا مثل باناز،
I found that these young men were torn apart
لقد وجدت أن هؤلاء الشبان مدمّرين
from trying to bridge the gaps
من محاولة سد الثغرات
between their families and the countries that they were born in.
بين أسرهم والبلدان التي ولدوا فيها.
And what I also learned is that extremist groups, terrorist groups
وما تعلمته أیضاً هو أن الجماعات المتطرفة والجماعات الإرهابية
are taking advantage of these feelings of our young people
يستغلون مشاعر شبابنا
and channeling that -- cynically -- channeling that toward violence.
ويوجّهونها - على نحو ساخر- يوجّهونها نحو العنف.
"Come to us," they say.
يقولون: "تعالوا إلينا".
"Reject both sides, your family and your country
"انبذوا كلا الطرفين، عائلاتكم وبلدانكم
because they reject you.
لأنهم رفضوكم.
For your family, their honor is more important than you
بالنسبة لعائلتك، يعدّ شرفهم أكثر أهمية منك
and for your country,
وبالنسبة لبلدك،
a real Norwegian, Brit or a French person will always be white and never you."
سيكون دائماً النرويجي أو البريطاني أو الفرنسي الأصيل أبيض وأنت لا."
They're also promising our young people the things that they crave:
كما أنهم يعدون شبابنا بأشياء يتوقون إليها:
significance, heroism, a sense of belonging and purpose,
الأهمية والبطولة والشعور بالانتماء ووجود هدف
a community that loves and accepts them.
مجتمع يحبهم ويقبل بهم.
They make the powerless feel powerful.
يجعلون الضعيف يشعر بالقوة.
The invisible and the silent are finally seen and heard.
أصبح الشخص غير المرئي والصامت مرئيًا ومسموعًا.
This is what they're doing for our young people.
هذا ما يفعلونه لشبابنا.
Why are these groups doing this for our young people and not us?
لماذا تقوم هذه المجموعات بذلك لشبابنا وليس لنا؟
The thing is,
كل ما في الأمر هو،
I'm not trying to justify
أنا لا أحاول أن أبرّر
or excuse any of the violence.
أو أقدّم عذراً لأي عنف.
What I am trying to say is that we have to understand
ما أحاول قوله هو أن علينا فهم
why some of our young people are attracted to this.
السبب من وراء انجذاب شبابنا لهذا الأمر.
I would like to also show you, actually --
وأود أيضًا أن أقدّم لكم، في الواقع --
these are childhood photos of some of the guys in the film.
هذه صور طفولة بعض الأشخاص الموجودين في الفيلم.
What really struck me is that so many of them --
ما أدهشني حقاً هو أن العديد منهم --
I never would have thought this --
لم أكن أعتقد ذلك أبداً --
but so many of them have absent or abusive fathers.
ولكن آباء الكثيرين منهم غائبون أو متعسّفون.
And several of these young guys
والعديد من هؤلاء الشباب
ended up finding caring and compassionate father figures
انتهى بهم المطاف إلى إيجاد الرعاية وصورة الأب الرحيمة
within these extremist groups.
داخل هذه الجماعات المتطرفة.
I also found men brutalized by racist violence,
كما وجدت رجالًا تجردوا من إنسانيّتهم بسبب العنف العرقي،
but who found a way to stop feeling like victims
ولكنهم وجدوا وسيلة لوقف الشعور بكونهم الضحايا
by becoming violent themselves.
بأن يصبحوا عنيفبن هم أيضًا.
In fact, I found something, to my horror, that I recognized.
في الواقع، وجدت شيئاً، أثار خوفي، أعرفه.
I found the same feelings that I felt as a 17-year-old as I fled from Norway.
وجدت نفس المشاعر التي شعرت بها في ال 17 من عمري عندما هربت من النرويج.
The same confusion, the same sorrow,
نفس الارتباك، نفس الحزن،
the same feeling of being betrayed
نفس الشعور بالتعرض للخيانة
and not belonging to anyone.
وعدم الانتماء إلى أيّ شخص.
The same feeling of being lost and torn between cultures.
نفس الشعور بالضياع والتمزّق بين الثقافات.
Having said that, I did not choose destruction,
بقولي ذلك، لم أختر الدمار،
I chose to pick up a camera instead of a gun.
اخترت حمل الكاميرا بدلًا من السلاح.
And the reason I did that is because of my superpower.
ويعود السبب لقيامي بذلك إلى قوتي العظيمة.
I could see that understanding is the answer, instead of violence.
ويمكنني أن أدرك أن الفهم هو الجواب، عوضًا عن العنف.
Seeing human beings
رؤية البشر
with all their virtues and all their flaws
مع كل مزاياهم وكل عيوبهم
instead of continuing the caricatures:
بدلاً من استمرار الرسوم الكاريكاتورية:
the us and them, the villains and victims.
نحن وهم، الأشرار والضحايا.
I'd also finally come to terms with the fact
وأود أخيرًا إبراز حقيقة
that my two cultures didn't have to be on a collision course
أنه لا يجب أن تكون ثقافة بلديّ في تصادم
but instead became a space where I found my own voice.
ولكن بدلًا من ذلك تصبحان مجالًا أعبر فيه عن ذاتي.
I stopped feeling like I had to pick a side,
توقفت عن الشعور بأنه عليّ الانحياز لطرف واحد،
but this took me many, many years.
ولكن هذا تطلّب مني سنوات طويلة.
There are so many of our young people today
هناك الكثير من شبابنا اليوم
who are struggling with these same issues,
يواجهون نفس هذه القضايا،
and they're struggling with this alone.
ويكافحون لوحدهم.
And this leaves them open like wounds.
وهذا يتركهم مفتوحين مثل الجروح.
And for some, the worldview of radical Islam
وبالنسبة للبعض، أصبحت النظرة العالمية للإسلام الراديكالي
becomes the infection that festers in these open wounds.
العدوى التي تنقض على هذه الجروح المفتوحة.
There's an African proverb that says,
هناك مثل إفريقي يقول،
"If the young are not initiated into the village,
"إذا لم يتم إعتبار الشباب طرفًا في القرية،
they will burn it down just to feel its warmth."
فسيقوم بإحراقها ليشعر بالدفء".
I would like to ask --
وأود أن أسأل --
to Muslim parents and Muslim communities,
الآباء المسلمين والمجتمعات المسلمة،
will you love and care for your children
هل سيحبون أطفالهم ويقومون برعايتهم
without forcing them to meet your expectations?
دون إجبارهم على تلبية توقعاتهم؟
Can you choose them instead of your honor?
يمكنكم اختيارهم بدلًا من شرفكم؟
Can you understand why they're so angry and alienated
هل يمكنكم فهم سبب غضبهم الشديد والغريب
when you put your honor before their happiness?
عندما تضعون شرفكم قبل سعادتهم؟
Can you try to be a friend to your child
هل يمكنكم أن تكونوا أصدقاء لأطفالكم
so that they can trust you
حتى يتمكنوا من الوثوق بكم
and want to share with you their experiences,
ويريدون مشاركتكم تجاربهم،
rather than having to seek it somewhere else?
بدلًا من البحث عن ذلك في مكان آخر؟
And to our young people tempted by extremism,
ولشبابنا الذين يغريهم التطرف،
can you acknowledge that your rage is fueled by pain?
هل يمكنكم الاعتراف أن الغضب الذي ينتابكم يغذيه الألم؟
Will you find the strength to resist those cynical old men
هل سيكون لديكم القوة لمقاومة هؤلاء الرجال المتشائمين
who want to use your blood for their own profits?
الذين يريدون استغلالكم لتحقيق أهدافهم؟
Can you find a way to live?
هل يمكنكم إيجاد وسيلة للعيش؟
Can you see that the sweetest revenge
هل يمكنكم رؤية أن أحلى انتقام
is for you to live a happy, full and free life?
هو أن تعيش حياة سعيدة وكاملة وحرة؟
A life defined by you and nobody else.
أنت من تحدد حياتك وليس أي شخص آخر.
Why do you want to become just another dead Muslim kid?
لماذا تريد أن تصبح مجرد طفل مسلم آخر ميت؟
And for the rest of us, when will we start listening to our young people?
وبالنسبة للبقية الباقية منا، متى سنستمع إلى شبابنا؟
How can we support them
كيف يمكننا دعمهم
in redirecting their pain into something more constructive?
لتوجيه آلامهم نحو أمر هادف؟
They think we don't like them.
يعتقدون أننا لا نحبهم.
They think we don't care what happens to them.
هم يعتقدون أننا لا نهتم لما حدث لهم.
They think we don't accept them.
وهم يعتقدون أننا لا نقبلهم.
Can we find a way to make them feel differently?
هل يمكننا إيجاد وسيلة لجعلهم يشعرون بالاختلاف؟
What will it take for us to see them and notice them
ما الذي سيتطلبه منا رؤيتهم والشعور بهم
before they become either the victims or the perpetrators of violence?
قبل أن يصبحوا من ضحايا العنف أو مرتكبيه؟
Can we make ourselves care about them and consider them to be our own?
هل يمكننا أن نهتم بأنفسنا واعتبارهم جزءاً منا؟
And not just be outraged when the victims of violence look like ourselves?
وليس فقط الشعور بالغضب عندما يكون ضحايا العنف منا؟
Can we find a way to reject hatred and heal the divisions between us?
هل يمكننا إيجاد طريقة لرفض الكراهية وإيجاد حل للانفصال الموجود بيننا؟
The thing is we cannot afford to give up on each other or on our kids,
لا يمكننا تحمل التخلي عن بعضنا البعض أو عن أطفالنا،
even if they've given up on us.
حتى لو تخلى عنا.
We are all in this together.
نحن جميعًا في هذا معًا.
And in the long term, revenge and violence will not work against extremists.
وعلى المدى الطويل، لن يجدي الانتقام والعنف نفعًا ضد المتطرفين.
Terrorists want us to huddle in our houses in fear,
يريد الإرهابيون منا الاختباء في بيوتنا من الخوف،
closing our doors and our hearts.
غلق الأبواب على أنفسنا، وغلق قلوبنا.
They want us to tear open more wounds in our societies
يريدون التسبب بالمزيد من الجروح في مجتمعاتنا
so that they can use them to spread their infection more widely.
ليتمكنوا من استغلالها لنشر العدوى على نطاق أوسع.
They want us to become like them:
يريدوننا أن نصبح مثلهم:
intolerant, hateful and cruel.
متعصّبين ويملئ الكره قلوبنا وقاسين.
The day after the Paris attacks,
في اليوم التالي لهجمات باريس،
a friend of mine sent this photo of her daughter.
أرسلت صديقتي هذه الصورة إلى ابنتها.
This is a white girl and an Arab girl.
هذه فتاة بيضاء البشرة وفتاة مسلمة.
They're best friends.
هن صديقتان مقرّبتان.
This image is the kryptonite for extremists.
تعدّى هذه الصورة مثل الكريبتونيت بالنسبة للمتطرفين.
These two little girls with their superpowers
هاتين الفتاتين الصغيرتين ذاتا القوة العظمى
are showing the way forward
ترسمان ملامح الطريق
towards a society that we need to build together,
نحو مجتمع نحتاج إلى بنائه معًا،
a society that includes and supports,
مجتمع يضم ويدعم،
rather than rejects our kids.
بدلًا من رفض أطفالنا.
Thank you for listening.
شكرًا على استماعكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)